<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article id="quotes">
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Quotes from Users</title>

    <author>
      <firstname>Tom</firstname>

      <surname>Eastep</surname>
    </author>

    <pubdate>2003-07-01</pubdate>

    <copyright>
      <year>2003</year>

      <holder>Thomas M Eastep</holder>
    </copyright>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
      document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version
      1.2 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with
      no Invariant Sections, with no Front-Cover, and with no Back-Cover
      Texts. A copy of the license is included in the section entitled &#34;<ulink
      url="GnuCopyright.htm">GNU Free Documentation License</ulink>&#34;.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </articleinfo>

  <section>
    <title>What Users are saying...</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>&#34;I have fought with IPtables for untold hours. First I tried
        the SuSE firewall, which worked for 80% of what I needed. Then
        gShield, which also worked for 80%. Then I set out to write my own
        IPtables parser in shell and awk, which was a lot of fun but never got
        me past the &#34;hey, cool&#34; stage. Then I discovered Shorewall.
        After about an hour, everything just worked. I am stunned, and very
        grateful&#34; -- ES, Phoenix AZ, USA.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>&#34;The configuration is intuitive and flexible, and much
        easier than any of the other iptables-based firewall programs out
        there. After sifting through many other scripts, it is obvious that
        yours is the most well thought-out and complete one available.&#34; --
        BC, USA</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>&#34;I just installed Shorewall after weeks of messing with
        ipchains/iptables and I had it up and running in under 20
        minutes!&#34; -- JL, Ohio</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>&#34;My case was almost like [the one above]. Well. instead of
        &#39;weeks&#39; it was &#39;months&#39; for me, and I think I needed
        two minutes more:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>One to see that I had no Internet access from the firewall
            itself.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Other to see that this was the default configuration, and it
            was enough to uncomment a line in /etc/shorewall/policy.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Minutes instead of months! Congratulations and thanks for such a
        simple and well documented thing for something as huge as
        iptables.&#34; -- JV, Spain.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>&#34;I downloaded Shorewall 1.2.0 and installed it on Mandrake
        8.1 without any problems. Your documentation is great and I really
        appreciate your network configuration info. That really helped me out
        alot. THANKS!!!&#34; -- MM.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>&#34;[Shorewall is a] great, great project. I&#39;ve used/tested
        may firewall scripts but this one is till now the best.&#34; -- B.R,
        Netherlands</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>&#34;Never in my +12 year career as a sys admin have I witnessed
        someone so relentless in developing a secure, state of the art, safe
        and useful product as the Shorewall firewall package for no cost or
        obligation involved.&#34; -- Mario Kerecki, Toronto</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>&#34;one time more to report, that your great shorewall in the
        latest release 1.2.9 is working fine for me with SuSE Linux 7.3! I now
        have 7 machines up and running with shorewall on several versions -
        starting with 1.2.2 up to the new 1.2.9 and I never have encountered
        any problems!&#34; -- SM, Germany</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>&#34;You have the best support of any other package I&#39;ve
        ever used.&#34; -- SE, US</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>&#34;Because our company has information which has been
        classified by the national government as secret, our security
        doesn&#39;t stop by putting a fence around our company. Information
        security is a hot issue. We also make use of checkpoint firewalls, but
        not all of the internet servers are guarded by checkpoint, some of
        them are running....Shorewall.&#34; -- Name withheld by request,
        Europe</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>&#34;thanx for all your efforts you put into shorewall - this
        product stands out against a lot of commercial stuff i´ve been working
        with in terms of flexibillity, quality &#38; support&#34; -- RM,
        Austria</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>&#34;I have never seen such a complete firewall package that is
        so easy to configure. I searched the Debian package system for
        firewall scripts and Shorewall won hands down.&#34; -- RG, Toronto</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>&#34;My respects... I&#39;ve just found and installed Shorewall
        1.3.3-1 and it is a wonderful piece of software. I&#39;ve just sent
        out an email to about 30 people recommending it. :-)</para>

        <para>While I had previously taken the time (maybe 40 hours) to really
        understand ipchains, then spent at least an hour per server
        customizing and carefully scrutinizing firewall rules, I&#39;ve got
        shorewall running on my home firewall, with rulesets and policies that
        I know make sense, in under 20 minutes.&#34; -- RP, Guatamala</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</article>