<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article id="IPIP">
  <!--$Id$-->

  <articleinfo>
    <title>Shorewall Support Guide</title>

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Tom</firstname>

        <surname>Eastep</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <pubdate>2003-12-18</pubdate>

    <copyright>
      <year>2001-2003</year>

      <holder>Thomas M. Eastep</holder>
    </copyright>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
      document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version
      1.2 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with
      no Invariant Sections, with no Front-Cover, and with no Back-Cover
      Texts. A copy of the license is included in the section entitled
      <quote><ulink url="GnuCopyright.htm">GNU Free Documentation License</ulink></quote>.</para>
    </legalnotice>

    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>1.1</revnumber>

        <date>2003-12-19</date>

        <authorinitials>TE</authorinitials>

        <revremark>Corrected URL for Newbies List</revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </articleinfo>

  <graphic fileref="images/obrasinf.gif" format="GIF" valign="middle" />

  <section>
    <title>Before Reporting a Problem or Asking a Question</title>

    <para>There are a number of sources of Shorewall information. Please try
    these before you post.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Shorewall versions earlier that 1.3.0 are no longer supported.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>More than half of the questions posted on the support list have
        answers directly accessible from the <ulink
        url="http://shorewall.net/shorewall_quickstart_guide.htm#Documentation">Documentation
        Index</ulink></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The <ulink url="FAQ.htm">FAQ</ulink> has solutions to more than
        30 common problems.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The <ulink url="troubleshoot.htm">Troubleshooting Information</ulink>
        contains a number of tips to help you solve common problems.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The <ulink url="errata.htm">Errata</ulink> has links to download
        updated components.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The <ulink url="http://lists.shorewall.net/htdig/search.html">Site
        and Mailing List Archives search facility</ulink> can locate documents
        and posts about similar problems:</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Problem Reporting Guidelines</title>

    <note>
      <para>In this section, commands that are to be entered to a root shell
      on your firewall system are underlined or are shown in a box with a
      colored background.</para>
    </note>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Please remember we only know what is posted in your message. Do
        not leave out any information that appears to be correct, or was
        mentioned in a previous post. There have been countless posts by
        people who were sure that some part of their configuration was correct
        when it actually contained a small error. We tend to be skeptics where
        detail is lacking.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Please keep in mind that you&#39;re asking for <emphasis
        role="bold">free</emphasis> technical support. Any help we offer is an
        act of generosity, not an obligation. Try to make it easy for us to
        help you. Follow good, courteous practices in writing and formatting
        your e-mail. Provide details that we need if you expect good answers.
        Exact quoting of error messages, log entries, command output, and
        other output is better than a paraphrase or summary.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Please don&#39;t describe your problem as <quote>Computer A
        can&#39;t see Computer B</quote>. Of course it can&#39;t -- it
        hasn&#39;t any eyes! If ping from A to B fails, say so (and see below
        for information about reporting <quote>ping</quote> problems). If
        Computer B doesn&#39;t show up in <quote>Network Neighborhood</quote>
        then say so.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Please give details about what doesn&#39;t work. Reports that
        say <quote>I followed the directions and it didn&#39;t work</quote>
        will elicit sympathy but probably little in the way of help. Again --
        if ping from A to B fails, say so (and see below for information about
        reporting <quote>ping</quote> problems). If Computer B doesn&#39;t
        show up in <quote>Network Neighborhood</quote> then say so. If access
        by IP address works but by DNS names it doesn&#39;t then say so.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Please don&#39;t describe your environment and then ask us to
        send you custom configuration files. We&#39;re here to answer your
        questions but we can&#39;t do your job for you.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>When reporting a problem, <emphasis role="bold">ALWAYS</emphasis>
        include this information:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>the exact version of Shorewall you are running.</para>

            <programlisting>shorewall version</programlisting>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>the complete, exact output of</para>

            <programlisting>ip addr show</programlisting>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>the complete, exact output of</para>

            <programlisting>ip route show</programlisting>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">THIS IS IMPORTANT!</emphasis> If your
            problem is that some type of connection to/from or through your
            firewall isn&#39;t working then please perform the following four
            steps:</para>

            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">If shorewall isn&#39;t running</emphasis>
                then <emphasis role="underline">/sbin/shorewall/start</emphasis>.
                <emphasis role="bold">Otherwise</emphasis> <emphasis
                role="underline">/sbin/shorewall reset</emphasis>.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Try making the connection that is failing.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="underline">/sbin/shorewall status &#62;
                /tmp/status.txt</emphasis></para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Post the /tmp/status.txt file as an attachment (you may
                compress it if you like).</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>the exact wording of any ping failure responses</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">If you installed Shorewall using one
            of the QuickStart Guides, please indicate which one</emphasis>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>As a general matter, <emphasis role="bold">please do not edit
        the diagnostic information</emphasis> in an attempt to conceal your IP
        address, netmask, nameserver addresses, domain name, etc. These
        aren&#39;t secrets, and concealing them often misleads us (and 80% of
        the time, a hacker could derive them anyway from information contained
        in the SMTP headers of your post).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Do you see any <quote>Shorewall</quote> messages (<quote><emphasis
        role="underline">/sbin/shorewall show log</emphasis></quote>) when you
        exercise the function that is giving you problems? If so, include the
        message(s) in your post along with a copy of your
        /etc/shorewall/interfaces file.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Please include any of the Shorewall configuration files
        (especially the /etc/shorewall/hosts file if you have modified that
        file) that you think are relevant. If you include
        /etc/shorewall/rules, please include /etc/shorewall/policy as well
        (rules are meaningless unless one also knows the policies).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>If an error occurs when you try to <quote><emphasis
        role="underline">shorewall start</emphasis></quote>, include a trace
        (See the Troubleshooting section for instructions).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">The list server limits posts to 120kb so
        don&#39;t post GIFs of your network layout, etc. to the Mailing List
        -- your post will be rejected</emphasis>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The author gratefully acknowleges that the above list was
        heavily plagiarized from the excellent LEAF document by
        <emphasis>Ray Olszewski</emphasis> found at <ulink
        url="http://leaf-project.org/pub/doc/docmanager/docid_1891.html">http://leaf-project.org/pub/doc/docmanager/docid_1891.html</ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>When using the mailing list, please post in plain text</title>

    <para>A growing number of MTAs serving list subscribers are rejecting all
    HTML traffic. At least one MTA has gone so far as to blacklist
    shorewall.net <quote>for continuous abuse</quote> because it has been my
    policy to allow HTML in list posts!!</para>

    <para>I think that blocking all HTML is a Draconian way to control spam
    and that the ultimate losers here are not the spammers but the list
    subscribers whose MTAs are bouncing all shorewall.net mail. As one list
    subscriber wrote to me privately <quote>These e-mail admin&#39;s need to
    get a (expletive deleted) life instead of trying to rid the planet of HTML
    based e-mail</quote>. Nevertheless, to allow subscribers to receive list
    posts as must as possible, I have now configured the list server at
    shorewall.net to convert all HTML to plain text. These converted posts are
    difficult to read so all of us will appreciate it if you just post in
    plain text to begin with.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Where to Send your Problem Report or to Ask for Help</title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">If you run Shorewall under Bering </emphasis>--
    please post your question or problem to <ulink
    url="mailto:leaf-user@lists.sourceforge.net">the LEAF Users mailing list</ulink>.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">If you are new to Shorewall and have a
    question or need help with a problem</emphasis>, please post to the <ulink
    url="mailto:shorewall-newbies@lists.shorewall.net">Shorewall Newbies
    mailing list</ulink>.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">If you run Shorewall under MandrakeSoft Multi
    Network Firewall (MNF) and you have not purchased an MNF license from
    MandrakeSoft then you can post non MNF-specific Shorewall questions to the
    <ulink url="mailto:shorewall-users@lists.shorewall.net">Shorewall users
    mailing list</ulink>. Do not expect to get free MNF support on the list</emphasis>.</para>

    <para>Otherwise, please post your question or problem to the <ulink
    url="mailto:shorewall-users@lists.shorewall.net">Shorewall users mailing
    list</ulink>. <emphasis role="bold">IMPORTANT</emphasis>: If you are not
    subscribed to the list, please say so -- otherwise, you will not be
    included in any replies.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Subscribing to the Newbies Mailing List</title>

    <para>To Subscribe to the mailing list go to <ulink
    url="https://lists.shorewall.net/mailman/listinfo/shorewall-newbies">https://lists.shorewall.net/mailman/listinfo/shorewall-newbies</ulink>.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Subscribing to the Users Mailing List</title>

    <para>To Subscribe to the mailing list go to <ulink
    url="https://lists.shorewall.net/mailman/listinfo/shorewall-users">https://lists.shorewall.net/mailman/listinfo/shorewall-users</ulink>.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Other Mailing Lists</title>

    <para>For information on other Shorewall mailing lists, go to <ulink
    url="http://lists.shorewall.net">http://lists.shorewall.net</ulink> .</para>
  </section>
</article>