<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Shorewall Errata</title>

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Tom</firstname>

        <surname>Eastep</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <pubdate>2005-09-02</pubdate>

    <copyright>
      <year>2001-2005</year>

      <holder>Thomas M. Eastep</holder>
    </copyright>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
      document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version
      1.2 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with
      no Invariant Sections, with no Front-Cover, and with no Back-Cover
      Texts. A copy of the license is included in the section entitled
      <quote><ulink url="GnuCopyright.htm">GNU Free Documentation
      License</ulink></quote>.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </articleinfo>

  <caution>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>If you use a Windows system to download a corrected script, be
        sure to run the script through <ulink
        url="http://www.megaloman.com/~hany/software/hd2u/">dos2unix</ulink>
        after you have moved it to your Linux system.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>If you are installing Shorewall for the first time and plan to
        use the .tgz and install.sh script, you can untar the archive, replace
        the <quote>firewall</quote> script in the untarred directory with the
        one you downloaded below, and then run install.sh.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>When the instructions say to install a corrected firewall script
        in /usr/share/shorewall/firewall, you may rename the existing file
        before copying in the new file.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">DO NOT INSTALL CORRECTED COMPONENTS ON A
        RELEASE EARLIER THAN THE ONE THAT THEY ARE LISTED UNDER
        BELOW.</emphasis> For example, do NOT install the 2.0.2 firewall
        script if you are running 2.0.0-RC2</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </caution>

  <section>
    <title>Problems in Shorewall.</title>

    <para>Beginning with Shorewall version 2.2.0, errata <emphasis
    role="bold">will not be published on this page</emphasis>. Rather, the
    download directory for each version will contain:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>A <filename>known_problems.txt</filename> file. This file will
        list all known problems and will describe to any corrections or
        workarounds available.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>An <filename class="directory">errata</filename> sub-directory.
        This directory will contain updated components that correct problems
        listed in the <filename>known_problems.txt</filename> file.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Upgrade Issues</title>

    <para>The upgrade issues have moved to <ulink url="upgrade_issues.htm">a
    separate page</ulink>.</para>
  </section>
</article>