<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <!--$Id$-->

  <articleinfo>
    <title>Fallback and Uninstall</title>

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Tom</firstname>

        <surname>Eastep</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <pubdate>2001-03-26</pubdate>

    <copyright>
      <year>2001</year>

      <holder>Thomas M. Eastep</holder>
    </copyright>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
      document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version
      1.2 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with
      no Invariant Sections, with no Front-Cover, and with no Back-Cover
      Texts. A copy of the license is included in the section entitled
      <quote><ulink url="GnuCopyright.htm">GNU Free Documentation License</ulink></quote>.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </articleinfo>

  <section>
    <title>Falling Back to the Previous Version of Shorewall using the
    Fallback Script</title>

    <para>If you install Shorewall and discover that it doesn&#39;t work for
    you, you can fall back to your previously installed version. To do that:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>cd to the distribution directory for the version of Seattle
        Firewall that you are currently running (NOT the version that you want
        to fall back to).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Type <quote>./fallback.sh</quote></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <caution>
      <para>The fallback script will replace /etc/shorewall/policy,
      /etc/shorewall/rules, /etc/shorewall/interfaces, /etc/shorewall/nat,
      /etc/shorewall/proxyarp and /etc/shorewall/masq with the version of
      these files from before the current version was installed. Any changes
      to any of these files will be lost.</para>
    </caution>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Falling Back to the Previous Version of Shorewall using rpm</title>

    <para>If your previous version of Shorewall was installed using RPM, you
    may fall back to that version by typing <quote>rpm -Uvh --force &#60;old
    rpm&#62;</quote> at a root shell prompt (Example: <quote>rpm -Uvh --force
    /downloads/shorewall-3.1=0noarch.rpm</quote> would fall back to the 3.1-0
    version of Shorewall).</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Uninstalling Shorewall</title>

    <para>If you no longer wish to use Shorewall, you may remove it by:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>cd to the distribution directory for the version of Shorewall
        that you have installed.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>type <quote>./uninstall.sh</quote></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>If you installed using an rpm, at a root shell prompt type
    <quote>rpm -e shorewall</quote>.</para>
  </section>
</article>