<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <!--$Id$-->

  <articleinfo>
    <title>AUDIT Target Support</title>

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Tom</firstname>

        <surname>Eastep</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <pubdate><?dbtimestamp format="Y/m/d"?></pubdate>

    <copyright>
      <year>2011</year>

      <holder>Thomas M. Eastep</holder>
    </copyright>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
      document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version
      1.2 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with
      no Invariant Sections, with no Front-Cover, and with no Back-Cover
      Texts. A copy of the license is included in the section entitled
      <quote><ulink url="GnuCopyright.htm">GNU Free Documentation
      License</ulink></quote>.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </articleinfo>

  <section>
    <title>Background</title>

    <para>In early 2011, Thomas Graf submitted a set of patches to the
    Netfilter development list that implemented an AUDIT rule target. This is
    from the initial submittal:</para>

    <blockquote>
      <para>This patch adds a new netfilter target which creates audit records
      for packets traversing a certain chain. It can be used to record packets
      which are rejected administraively as follows:</para>

      <simplelist>
        <member>-N AUDIT_DROP</member>

        <member>-A AUDIT_DROP -j AUDIT --type DROP</member>

        <member>-A AUDIT_DROP -j DROP</member>
      </simplelist>

      <para>A rule which would typically drop or reject a packet would then
      invoke the new chain to record packets before dropping them.</para>

      <simplelist>
        <member>-j AUDIT_DROP</member>
      </simplelist>

      <para>The module is protocol independant and works for iptables,
      ip6tables and ebtables.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>netfilter hook</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>packet length</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>incoming/outgoing interface</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>MAC src/dst/proto for ethernet packets</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>src/dst/protocol address for IPv4/IPv6</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>src/dst port for TCP/UDP/UDPLITE</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>icmp type/code</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </blockquote>

    <para>The audited packets are sent to a daemon (auditd) that write the
    audit information to a log file.</para>

    <para>In a related post by Eric Paris, the following additional
    information was posted:</para>

    <blockquote>
      <para>AUDIT exists because a very large number of gov't customers (Not
      just USA) have special requirements about how 'relevant' information is
      gathered and stored. They require centralization and standardization and
      require pretty formal documentation describing it's operation. The gov't
      certification authority has recently added a requirement that they be
      able to log 'illegal attempted network connections' via the approved
      audit facility. Thus, this patch.</para>
    </blockquote>

    <para>The AUDIT target was included in Linux kernel 2.6.39.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Shorewall Support</title>

    <para>Shorewall support for the AUDIT target was added in 4.4.20.</para>

    <para>The support involves the following:</para>

    <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
      <listitem>
        <para>A new "AUDIT Target" capability is added and is required for
        auditing support. To use AUDIT support with a capabilities file, that
        file must be generated using this or a later release.</para>

        <para>Use 'shorewall show capabilities' after installing this release
        to see if your kernel/iptables support the AUDIT target.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>In /etc/shorewall/policy's POLICY column, the policy (and
        default action, if any) may be followed by ':audit' to cause
        application of the policy to be audited. Only ACCEPT, DROP and REJECT
        policies may be audited.</para>

        <para>Example:</para>

        <programlisting>#SOURCE	DEST	POLICY		LOG
#				LEVEL
net	fw      DROP:audit</programlisting>

        <para>It is allowed to also specify a log level on audited policies
        resulting in both auditing and logging.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Three new builtin targets that may be used in the rules file, in
        macros and in other actions.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>A_ACCEPT - Audits and accepts the connection request</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>A_DROP - Audits and drops the connection request</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>A_REJECT - Audits and rejects</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>A log level may be supplied with these actions to provide both
        auditing and logging.</para>

        <para>Example:</para>

        <programlisting>#ACTION        SOURCE       DEST       PROTO
A_ACCEPT:info  loc          net        ...</programlisting>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The BLACKLIST_DISPOSITION, MACLIST_DISPOSITION,
        SMURF_DISPOSITION and TCP_FLAGS_DISPOSITION options may be set as
        follows:</para>

        <informaltable>
          <tgroup cols="2">
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>BLACKLIST_DISPOSITION</entry>

                <entry>A_DROP or A_REJECT</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>MACLIST_DISPOSITION</entry>

                <entry>A_DROP, A_REJECT unless MACLIST_TABLE=mangle</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>SMURF_DISPOSITION<footnote>
                    <para>This option was added in Shorewall 4.4.20</para>
                  </footnote></entry>

                <entry>A_DROP</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>TCP_FLAGS_DISPOSITION</entry>

                <entry>A_DROP or A_REJECT</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>An 'audit' option has been added to the /etc/shorewall/blacklist
        file which causes the packets matching the entryto be audited. 'audit'
        may not be specified together with 'accept'.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The builtin actions (dropBroadcast, rejNonSyn, etc.) now support
        an 'audit' parameter which causes all ACCEPT, DROP and REJECTs
        performed by the action to be audited. This allows creation of audited
        versions of the Shorewall-provided default actions (action.Drop and
        action.Reject).</para>

        <note>
          <para>The builtin actions are those actions listed in the output of
          <command>shorewall show actions</command> whose names begin with a
          lower-case letter.</para>
        </note>

        <para>Here's a version of action.Drop that does auditing:</para>

        <programlisting>#TARGET         SOURCE  DEST    PROTO   DPORT   SPORT
#
# Count packets that come through here
#
COUNT
#
# Reject 'auth'
#
A_REJECT        -       -       tcp     
#
# Don't log broadcasts
#
dropBcast(audit)
#
# ACCEPT critical ICMP types
#
AudAllowICMPs      -       -       icmp
#
# Drop packets that are in the INVALID state -- these are usually ICMP packets
# and just confuse people when they appear in the log.
#
dropInvalid(audit)
#
# Drop Microsoft noise so that it doesn't clutter up the log.
#
AudSMB(DROP)
AudDropUPnP
#
# Drop 'newnotsyn' traffic so that it doesn't get logged.
#
dropNotSyn(audit)  -       -       tcp
#
# Drop late-arriving DNS replies. These are just a nuisance and clutter up
# the log.
#
A_DROP          -       -       udp      -     53</programlisting>

        <para>The 'Aud...' macros would be auditing versions of their standard
        macro counterparts (if you are interested in auditing those connection
        types).</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
</article>
