<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <!--$Id$-->

  <articleinfo>
    <title>Shorewall Internals</title>

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Tom</firstname>

        <surname>Eastep</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <pubdate><?dbtimestamp format="Y/m/d"?></pubdate>

    <copyright>
      <year>2012</year>

      <holder>Thomas M. Eastep</holder>
    </copyright>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
      document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version
      1.2 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with
      no Invariant Sections, with no Front-Cover, and with no Back-Cover
      Texts. A copy of the license is included in the section entitled
      <quote><ulink url="GnuCopyright.htm">GNU Free Documentation
      License</ulink></quote>.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </articleinfo>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>This document provides an overview of Shorewall internals. It is
    intended to ease the task of approaching the Shorewall code base by
    providing a roadmap of what you will find there.</para>

    <section>
      <title>History</title>

      <para>Shorewall was originally written entirely in Bourne Shell. The
      chief advantage of this approach was that virtually any platform
      supports the shell, including small embedded environments. The initial
      release was in early 2001. This version ran iptables, ip, etc.
      immediately after processing the corresponding configuration entry. If
      an error was encountered, the firewall was stopped. For this reason, the
      <filename>routestopped</filename> file had to be very simple and
      foolproof.</para>

      <para>In Shorewall 3.2.0 (July 2006), the implementation was changed to
      use the current compile-then-execute architecture. This was
      accompilished by modifying the existing code rather than writing a
      compiler/generator from scratch. The resulting code was fragile and hard
      to maintain. 3.2.0 also marked the introduction of
      Shorewall-lite.</para>

      <para>By 2007, the compiler had become unmaintainable and needed to be
      rewritten. I made the decision to write the compiler in Perl and
      released it as a separate Shorewall-perl packets in Shorewall 4.0.0
      (July 2007). The shell-based compiler was packaged in a Shorewall-shell
      package. An option (SHOREWALL_COMPILER) in shorewall.conf specified
      which compiler to use. The Perl-based compiler was siginificantly
      faster, and the compiled script also ran much faster thanks to its use
      of iptables-restore.</para>

      <para>Shorewall6 was introduced in Shorewall 4.2.4 (December
      2008).</para>

      <para>Support for the old Shell-based compiler was eliminated in
      Shorewall 4.4.0 (July 2009).</para>

      <para>Shorewall 4.5.0 (February 2012) marked the introduction of the
      current architecture and packaging.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Architecture</title>

      <para>The components of the Shorewall product suite fall into five broad
      categories:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Build/Install subsystem</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Command Line Interface (CLI)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Run-time Libraries</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Compiler</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Configuration files (including actions and macros)</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <section>
        <title>Build/Install Subsystem</title>

        <para>The Shorewall Build/Install subsystem packages the products for
        release and installs them on an end-user's or a packager's system. It
        is diagrammed in the following graphic.</para>

        <graphic fileref="images/BuildInstall.png"/>

        <para>The build environment components are not released and are
        discussed in the <ulink url="Build.html">Shorewall Build
        Article</ulink>.</para>

        <para>The end-user/packager environment consists of the
        <filename>configure</filename> and <filename>configure.pl</filename>
        programs in Shorewall-core and an <filename>install.sh</filename>
        program in each product.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>CLI</title>

        <para>The CLI is written entirely in Bourne Shell so as to allow it to
        run on small embedded systems within the -lite products. The CLI
        programs themselves are very small; then set global variables then
        call into the CLI libraries. Here's an example
        (/sbin/shorewall):</para>

        <programlisting>PRODUCT=shorewall

#
# This is modified by the installer when ${SHAREDIR} != /usr/share
#
. /usr/share/shorewall/shorewallrc

g_program=$PRODUCT
g_libexec="$LIBEXECDIR"
g_sharedir="$SHAREDIR"/shorewall
g_sbindir="$SBINDIR"
g_perllib="$PERLLIBDIR"
g_confdir="$CONFDIR"/shorewall
g_readrc=1

. $g_sharedir/lib.cli

shorewall_cli $@</programlisting>

        <para>As you can see, it sets the PRODUCT variable, loads the
        shorewallrc file, sets the global variables (all of which have names
        beginning with "g_", loads <filename>lib.cli</filename>, and calls
        shorewall_cli passing its own arguments.</para>

        <para>There are two CLI libraries: <filename>lib.cli</filename> in
        Shorewall Core and <filename>lib.cli-std </filename>in Shorewall. The
        <filename>lib.cli</filename> library is always loaded by the CLI
        programs; <filename>lib-cli-std</filename> is also loaded when the
        product is 'shorewall' or 'shorewall6'.
        <filename>lib.cli-std</filename> overloads some functions in
        <filename>lib.cli</filename> and also provides logic for the
        additional commands supported by the full products.</para>

        <para>The CLI libraries load two additional Shell libraries from
        Shorewall.core: <filename>lib.base</filename> and
        <filename>lib.common</filename> (actually,
        <filename>lib.base</filename> loads <filename>lib.common</filename>).
        These libraries are separete from <filename>lib.cli</filename> for
        both historical and practicle reasons. <filename>lib.base</filename>
        (aka functions) can be loaded by application programs, although this
        was more common in the early years of Shorewall. In addition to being
        loaded by the CLIs, <filename>lib.common</filename> is also copied
        into the generated script by the compilers.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Run-time Libraries</title>

        <para>Thare are two libraries that are copied into the generated
        script by the compiler: <filename>lib.common</filename> from
        Shorewall-core and <filename>lib.core</filename> from Shorewall. The
        "outer block" of the generated script comes from the Shorewall file
        <filename>prog.footer</filename>.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="Compiler">
        <title>Compiler</title>

        <para>With the exception of the <filename>getparams</filename> Shell
        program, the compiler is written in Perl. The compiler main program is
        compiler.pl from Shorewall.conf; it's run-line arguments are described
        in the <ulink url="Shorewall-perl.html%23compiler.pl">Shorewall Perl
        Article</ulink>. It is invoked by the <emphasis>compiler</emphasis>
        function in <filename>lib.cli-std</filename>.</para>

        <para>The compiler is modularized as follows:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><filename>Accounting.pm</filename> (Shorewall::Accounting).
            Processes the <filename>accounting</filename> file.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>Chains.pm</filename> (Shorewall::Chains). This is
            the module that provides an interface to iptables/Netfilter for
            the other modules. The optimizer is included in this
            module.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>Config.pm</filename> (Shorewall::Config). This is
            a multi-purpose module that supplies several related
            services:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Error and Progress message production.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Pre-processor. Supplies all configuration file handling
                including variable expansion, ?IF...?ELSE...?ENDIF processing,
                INCLUDE directives and embedded Shell and Perl.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Output script file creation with functions to write into
                the script. The latter functions are no-ops when the
                <command>check</command> command is being executed.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Capability Detection</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Miscellaneous utility functions.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>Compiler.pm</filename> (Shorewall::Compiler). The
            compiler() function in this module contains the top-leve of the
            compiler.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>IPAddrs.pm</filename> (Shorewall::IPAddrs) - IP
            Address validation and manipulation (both IPv4 and IPv6). Also
            interfaces to NSS for protocol/service name resolution.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>Misc.pm</filename> (Shorewall::Misc) - Provides
            services that don't fit well into the other modules.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>Nat.pm</filename> (Shorewall::Nat) - Handles all
            nat table rules. Processes the <filename>masq</filename>,
            <filename>nat</filename> and <filename>netmap</filename>
            files.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>Proc.pm</filename> (Shorewall::Proc) - Handles
            manipulation of <filename>/proc/sys/</filename>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>Providers.pm</filename> (Shorewall::Providers) -
            Handles policy routing; processes the
            <filename>providers</filename> file.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>Proxyarp.pm</filename> (Shorewall::Proxyarp) -
            Processes the <filename>proxyarp</filename> file.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>Raw.pm</filename> (Shorewall::Raw) - Handles the
            raw table; processes the <filename>conntrack</filename> (formerly
            <filename>notrack</filename>) file.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>Rules.pm</filename> (Shorewall::Rules) - Contains
            the logic for process the <filename>policy</filename> and
            <filename>rules</filename> files, including
            <filename>macros</filename> and
            <filename>actions</filename>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>Tc.pm</filename> (Shorewall::Tc) - Handles traffic
            shaping.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>Tunnels.pm</filename> (Shorewall::Tunnels) -
            Processes the <filename>tunnels</filename> file.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>Zones.pm</filename> (Shorewall::Zones) - Processes
            the <filename>zones</filename>, <filename>interfaces</filename>
            and <filename>hosts</filename> files. Provides the interface to
            zones and interfaces to the other modules.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>Because the params file can contain arbitrary shell code, it
        must be processed by a shell. The body of
        <filename>getparams</filename> is as follows:</para>

        <programlisting>#  Parameters:
#
#      $1 = Path name of params file
#      $2 = $CONFIG_PATH
#      $3 = Address family (4 or 6)
#
if [ "$3" = 6 ]; then
    PRODUCT=shorewall6
else
    PRODUCT=shorewall
fi

#
# This is modified by the installer when ${SHAREDIR} != /usr/share
#
. /usr/share/shorewall/shorewallrc

g_program="$PRODUCT"
g_libexec="$LIBEXECDIR"
g_sharedir="$SHAREDIR"/shorewall
g_sbindir="$SBINDIR"
g_perllib="$PERLLIBDIR"
g_confdir="$CONFDIR/$PRODUCT"
g_readrc=1

. $g_sharedir/lib.cli

CONFIG_PATH="$2"

set -a

. $1 &gt;&amp;2 # Avoid spurious output on STDOUT

set +a

export -p</programlisting>

        <para>The program establishes the environment of the Shorewall or
        Shoreall6 CLI program since that is the environment in which the
        <filename>params</filename> file has been traditionally processed. It
        then sets the -<option>a</option> option so that all newly-created
        variables will be exported and invokes the
        <filename><filename>params</filename></filename> file. Because the
        STDOUT file is a pipe back to the compiler, no spurious output must be
        sent to that file; so <filename>getparams</filename> redirect
        <filename>params</filename> output to STDOUT. After the script has
        executed, an <command>export -p</command> command is executed to send
        the contents of the environ array back to the compiler.</para>

        <para>Regrettably, the various shells (and even different versions of
        the same shell) produce quite different output from <command>export
        -p</command>. The Perl function Shorewall::Config::getparams() detects
        which species of shell was being used and stores the variable settings
        into the %params hash. Variables that are also in %ENV are only stored
        in %params if there value in the output from the
        <filename>getparams</filename> script is different from that in
        %ENV.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Configuration Files</title>

        <para>The configuration files are all well-documented. About the only
        thing worth noting is that some macros and actions are duplicated in
        the Shorewall and Shorewall6 packages. Because the Shorewall6 default
        CONFIG_PATH looks in ${SHAREDIR}/shorewall6 before looking in
        ${SHARDIR_/shorewall, this allows Shorewall6 to implement
        IPv6-specific handling where required.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The Generated Script</title>

      <para>The generated script is completely self-contained so as to avoid
      version dependencies between the Shorewall version used to create the
      script and the version of Shorewall-common installed on the remote
      firewall.</para>

      <para>The operation of the generated script is illustrated in this
      diagram.</para>

      <graphic fileref="images/RunningScript.png"/>

      <para>The Netfilter ruleset is sometimes dependent on the environment
      when the script runs. Dynamic IP addresses and gateways, for example,
      must be detected when the script runs. As a consequence, it is the
      generated script and not the compiler that creates the input for
      iptables-restore. While that input could be passed to iptables-restore
      in a pipe, it is written to
      <filename>${VARDIR}/.iptables_restore-input</filename> so that it is
      available for post-mortem analysis in the event that iptables-restore
      fails. For the other utilities (ip, tc, ipset, etc), the script runs
      them passing their input on the run-line.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Compiler Internals</title>

    <para>Because the compiler is the most complex part of the Shorewall
    product suite, I've chosen to document it first. Before diving into the
    details of the individual modules, lets take a look at a few general
    things.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Modularization</title>

      <para>While the compiler is modularized and uses encapsulation, it is
      not object-oriented. This is due to the fact that much of the compiler
      was written by manually translating the earlier Shell code.</para>

      <para>Module data is not completely encapsulated. Heavily used tables,
      most notably the Chain Table (%chain_table) in Shorewall::Chains is
      exported for read access. Updates to module data is always
      encapsulated.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Module Initialization</title>

      <para>While currently unused and untested, the Compiler modules are
      designed to be able to be loaded into a parent Perl program and the
      compiler executed repeatedly without unloading the modules. To
      accomodate that usage scenario, variable data is not initialized at
      declaration time or in an INIT block, but is rather initialized in an
      <firstterm>initialize</firstterm> function. Because off of these
      functions have the same name ("initialize"), they are not exported but
      are rather called using a fully-qualified name (e.g.,
      "Shorewall::Config::initialize").</para>

      <para>Most of the the initialization functions accept arguements. Those
      most common argument is the address family (4 or 6), depending on
      whether an IPv4 or IPv6 firewall is being compiled. Each of the modules
      that are address-family dependent have their own $family private (my)
      variable.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Module Dependence</title>

      <para>Here is the module dependency tree. To simplify the diagram,
      direct dependencies are not shown where there is also a transitive
      dependency.</para>

      <graphic fileref="images/ModuleDepencency.png"/>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Config Module</title>

      <para>As mentioned above, the Config module offers several related
      services. Each will be described in a separate sub-section.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Pre-processor</title>

        <para>Unlike preprocessors like ccp, the Shorewall pre-processor does
        it's work each time that the higher-level functions ask for the next
        line of input.</para>

        <para>The major exported functions in the pre-processor are:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>open_file( $ )</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The single argument names the file to be opened and is
              usually a simple filename such as
              <filename>shorewall.conf</filename>. <emphasis
              role="bold">open_file</emphasis> calls <emphasis
              role="bold">find_file</emphasis> who traverses the CONFIG_PATH
              looking for a file with the requested name. If the file is found
              and has non-zero size, it is opened and module-global variables
              are set as follows, and the fully-qualified name of the file is
              returned by the function.</para>

              <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                  <term>$currentfile</term>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>Handle for the file open</para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                  <term>$currentfilename (exported)</term>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>The fully-qualified name of the file.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                  <term>$currentlinenumber</term>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>Set to zero.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
              </variablelist>

              <para>If the file is not found or if it has zero size, false
              ('') is returned.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>push_open( $ )</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Sometimes, the higher-level modules need to suspend
              processing of the current file and open another file. An obvious
              example is when the Rules module needs to process a macro file.
              The push_open function is called in these cases.</para>

              <para><emphasis role="bold">push_open</emphasis> pushes
              <emphasis role="bold">$currentfile</emphasis>, <emphasis
              role="bold">$currentfilename</emphasis>, <emphasis
              role="bold">$currentlinenumber</emphasis> and <emphasis
              role="bold">$ifstack</emphasis> onto <emphasis
              role="bold">@includestack</emphasis>, copies <emphasis
              role="bold">@includestack</emphasis> into a local array, pushes
              a reference to the local array onto <emphasis
              role="bold">@openstack</emphasis>, and empties <emphasis
              role="bold">@includestack</emphasis></para>

              <para>As its final step, <emphasis
              role="bold">push_open</emphasis> calls <emphasis
              role="bold">open_file</emphasis>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>pop_open()</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The <emphasis role="bold">pop_open</emphasis> function
              must be called after the file opened by <emphasis
              role="bold">push_open</emphasis> is processed. This is true even
              in the case where <emphasis role="bold">push_open</emphasis>
              returned false.</para>

              <para><emphasis role="bold">pop_open</emphasis> pops <emphasis
              role="bold">@openstack</emphasis> and restores <emphasis
              role="bold">$currentfile</emphasis>, <emphasis
              role="bold">$currentfilename</emphasis>, <emphasis
              role="bold">$currentlinenumber</emphasis>, <emphasis
              role="bold">$ifstack</emphasis> and <emphasis
              role="bold">@includestack</emphasis>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>close_file()</term>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">close_file</emphasis> is called to
              close the current file. Higher-level modules should only call
              <emphasis role="bold">close_file</emphasis> to close the current
              file prior to end-of-file.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>first_entry( $ )</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>This function is called to determine what happens when the
              first non-commentary and no-blank line is read from the open
              file. The argument may be either a scalar or a function
              reference. If the argument is a scalar then it is treaded as a
              progress message that should be issued if the VERBOSITY setting
              is &gt;= 1. If the argument is a function reference, the
              function (usually a closure) is called.</para>

              <para><emphasis role="bold">first_entry</emphasis> may called
              after a successful call to <emphasis
              role="bold">open_file</emphasis>. If it is not called, then the
              pre-processor takes no action when the first non-blank
              non-commentary line is found.</para>

              <para><emphasis role="bold">first_entry</emphasis> returns no
              significant value.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>read_a_line( $ )</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>This function delivers the next logical input line to the
              caller. The single argument is defined by the following
              constants:</para>

              <programlisting>use constant { PLAIN_READ          =&gt; 0,     # No read_a_line options
               EMBEDDED_ENABLED    =&gt; 1,     # Look for embedded Shell and Perl
               EXPAND_VARIABLES    =&gt; 2,     # Expand Shell variables
               STRIP_COMMENTS      =&gt; 4,     # Remove comments
               SUPPRESS_WHITESPACE =&gt; 8,     # Ignore blank lines
               CHECK_GUNK          =&gt; 16,    # Look for unprintable characters
               CONFIG_CONTINUATION =&gt; 32,    # Suppress leading whitespace if
                                             # continued line ends in ',' or ':'
               DO_INCLUDE          =&gt; 64,    # Look for INCLUDE &lt;filename&gt;
               NORMAL_READ         =&gt; -1     # All options
            };</programlisting>

              <para>The actual argument may be a bit-wise OR of any of the
              above constants.</para>

              <para>The function does not return the logical line; that line
              is rather stored in the module-global variable <emphasis
              role="bold">$currentline</emphasis> (exported). The function
              simply returns true if a line was read or false if end-of-file
              was reached. <emphasis role="bold">read_a_line</emphasis>
              automatically calls <emphasis role="bold">close_file</emphasis>
              at EOF.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>split_line1</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Most of the callers of <emphasis
              role="bold">read_a_line</emphasis> want to treat each line as
              whitespace-separated columns. The <emphasis
              role="bold">split_line</emphasis> and <emphasis
              role="bold">split_line1</emphasis> functions return an array
              containing the contents of those columns.</para>

              <para>The arguments to split_line1 are:</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>A <option>name</option> =&gt;
                  <replaceable>column-number</replaceable> pair for each of
                  the columns in the file. These are used to handle lines that
                  use the <ulink
                  url="configuration_file_basics.htm#Pairs">alternate input
                  methods</ulink> and also serve to define the number of
                  columns in the file's records.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>A hash reference defining <option>keyword</option>
                  =&gt; <replaceable>number-of-columns</replaceable> pairs.
                  For example "{ COMMENT =&gt; 0, FORMAT 2 }" allows COMMENT
                  lines of an unlimited number of space-separated tokens and
                  it allows FORMAT lines with exactly two columns. </para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>

              <para>If there are fewer space-separated tokens on the line than
              specified in the arguments, then "-" is returned for the the
              trailing columns that were omitted.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>split_line</term>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">split_line</emphasis> simply returns
              <emphasis role="bold">split_line1( @_, {} )</emphasis>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Error and Progress Message Production</title>

        <para>There are several exported functions dealing with error and
        warning messages:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>fatal_error</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The argument(s) to this function describe the error. The
              generated error message is:</para>

              <simplelist>
                <member>"ERROR: @_" followed by the name of the file and the
                line number where the error occurred. </member>
              </simplelist>

              <para>The mesage is written to the STARTUP_LOG, if any.</para>

              <para>The function does not return but rather passes the message
              to <emphasis role="bold">die</emphasis> or to <emphasis
              role="bold">confess</emphasis>, depending on whether the "-T"
              option was specified.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>warning_message</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The warning_message is very similar to fatal_error but
              avoids calling <emphasis role="bold">die</emphasis> or <emphasis
              role="bold">confess</emphasis>. It also prefixes the argument(s)
              with "WARNING: " rather than "ERROR: ".</para>

              <para>It message is written to Standard Out and to the
              STARTUP_LOG, if any.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>progress_message, progress_message2, progress_message3 and
            progress_message_nocompress</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>These procedures conditionally write their argument(s) to
              Standard Out and to the STARTUP_LOG (if any), depending on the
              settings of VERBOSITY and and LOG_VERBOSITY respectively.</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">progress_message</emphasis> only
                  write messages when the verbosity is 2. This function also
                  preserves leading whitespace while removing superflous
                  embedded whitespace from the messages.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">progress_message2</emphasis>
                  writes messages with the verbosity is &gt;= 1.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">progress_message3</emphasis>
                  writes messages when the verbosity is &gt;= 0.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para><emphasis
                  role="bold">progress_message_nocompress</emphasis> is like
                  <emphasis role="bold">progress_message</emphasis> except
                  that it does not preserve leading whitespace nor does it
                  eliminate superfluous embedded whitespacve from the
                  messages.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title/>

        <para/>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>
