<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article id="quotes">
  <!--$Id$-->

  <articleinfo>
    <title>Quotes from Users</title>

    <author>
      <firstname>Tom</firstname>

      <surname>Eastep</surname>
    </author>

    <pubdate><?dbtimestamp format="Y/m/d"?></pubdate>

    <copyright>
      <year>2003</year>

      <year>2004</year>

      <holder>Thomas M Eastep</holder>
    </copyright>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
      document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version
      1.2 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with
      no Invariant Sections, with no Front-Cover, and with no Back-Cover
      Texts. A copy of the license is included in the section entitled
      <quote><ulink url="GnuCopyright.htm">GNU Free Documentation
      License</ulink></quote>.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </articleinfo>

  <section id="Quotes">
    <title>What Users are saying...</title>

    <blockquote>
      <attribution>AS, Poland</attribution>

      <para><emphasis>I want to say that Shorewall documentation is the best
      I've ever found on the net. It's helped me a lot in understanding how
      network is working. It is the best of breed. It contains not only
      Shorewall specific topics with the assumption that all the rest is well
      known, but also gives some very useful background information. Thank you
      very much for this wonderful piece of work. </emphasis></para>
    </blockquote>

    <blockquote>
      <attribution>ES, Phoenix AZ, USA</attribution>

      <para><emphasis>I have fought with IPtables for untold hours. First I
      tried the SUSE firewall, which worked for 80% of what I needed. Then
      gShield, which also worked for 80%. Then I set out to write my own
      IPtables parser in shell and awk, which was a lot of fun but never got
      me past the <quote>hey, cool</quote> stage. Then I discovered Shorewall.
      After about an hour, everything just worked. I am stunned, and very
      grateful</emphasis></para>
    </blockquote>

    <blockquote>
      <attribution>SE, California, USA</attribution>

      <para><emphasis>In two words, I'd call Shorewall "brilliant simplicity".
      Define general rules of what it is you want to do, and let the software
      determine the specific rules on how to implement it. It's great only
      having to define specific rules for specific instances. I have a much
      higher degree of confidence in my firewall than I have had previously.
      Thank you for Shorewall!.</emphasis></para>
    </blockquote>

    <blockquote>
      <attribution>BC, USA</attribution>

      <para><emphasis>The configuration is intuitive and flexible, and much
      easier than any of the other iptables-based firewall programs out there.
      After sifting through many other scripts, it is obvious that yours is
      the most well thought-out and complete one available.</emphasis></para>
    </blockquote>

    <blockquote>
      <attribution>JL, Ohio</attribution>

      <para><emphasis>I just installed Shorewall after weeks of messing with
      ipchains/iptables and I had it up and running in under 20
      minutes!</emphasis></para>
    </blockquote>

    <blockquote>
      <attribution>JV, Spain</attribution>

      <para><emphasis>My case was almost like [the one above]. Well. instead
      of <quote>weeks</quote> it was <quote>months</quote> for me, and I think
      I needed two minutes more:</emphasis></para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>One to see that I had no Internet access from the
          firewall itself.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Other to see that this was the default
          configuration, and it was enough to uncomment a line in
          /etc/shorewall/policy.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para><emphasis>Minutes instead of months! Congratulations and thanks
      for such a simple and well documented thing for something as huge as
      iptables</emphasis></para>
    </blockquote>

    <blockquote>
      <attribution>MM</attribution>

      <para><emphasis>I downloaded Shorewall 1.2.0 and installed it on
      Mandrake 8.1 without any problems. Your documentation is great and I
      really appreciate your network configuration info. That really helped me
      out alot. THANKS!!!</emphasis></para>
    </blockquote>

    <blockquote>
      <attribution>B.R, Netherlands</attribution>

      <para><emphasis>[Shorewall is a] great, great project. I've used/tested
      may firewall scripts but this one is till now the
      best.</emphasis></para>
    </blockquote>

    <blockquote>
      <attribution>Mario Kerecki, Toronto</attribution>

      <para><emphasis>Never in my +12 year career as a sys admin have I
      witnessed someone so relentless in developing a secure, state of the
      art, safe and useful product as the Shorewall firewall package for no
      cost or obligation involved.</emphasis></para>
    </blockquote>

    <blockquote>
      <attribution>SM, Germany</attribution>

      <para><emphasis>one time more to report, that your great shorewall in
      the latest release 1.2.9 is working fine for me with SUSE Linux 7.3! I
      now have 7 machines up and running with shorewall on several versions -
      starting with 1.2.2 up to the new 1.2.9 and I never have encountered any
      problems!</emphasis></para>
    </blockquote>

    <blockquote>
      <attribution>SE, US</attribution>

      <para><emphasis>You have the best support of any other package I've ever
      used.</emphasis></para>
    </blockquote>

    <blockquote>
      <attribution>Name withheld by request, Europe</attribution>

      <para><emphasis>Because our company has information which has been
      classified by the national government as secret, our security doesn't
      stop by putting a fence around our company. Information security is a
      hot issue. We also make use of checkpoint firewalls, but not all of the
      internet servers are guarded by checkpoint, some of them are
      running....Shorewall.</emphasis></para>
    </blockquote>

    <blockquote>
      <attribution>RM, Austria</attribution>

      <para><emphasis>thanx for all your efforts you put into shorewall - this
      product stands out against a lot of commercial stuff i´ve been working
      with in terms of flexibillity, quality &amp; support</emphasis></para>
    </blockquote>

    <blockquote>
      <attribution>RG, Toronto</attribution>

      <para><emphasis>I have never seen such a complete firewall package that
      is so easy to configure. I searched the Debian package system for
      firewall scripts and Shorewall won hands down.</emphasis></para>
    </blockquote>

    <blockquote>
      <attribution>RP, Guatamala</attribution>

      <para><emphasis>My respects... I've just found and installed Shorewall
      1.3.3-1 and it is a wonderful piece of software. I've just sent out an
      email to about 30 people recommending it. :-)</emphasis></para>

      <para><emphasis>While I had previously taken the time (maybe 40 hours)
      to really understand ipchains, then spent at least an hour per server
      customizing and carefully scrutinizing firewall rules, I've got
      shorewall running on my home firewall, with rulesets and policies that I
      know make sense, in under 20 minutes.</emphasis></para>
    </blockquote>
  </section>
</article>