<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<article id="Shorewall_and_Kazaa">
  <!--$Id$-->

  <articleinfo>
    <title>Kazaa Filtering</title>

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Tom</firstname>

        <surname>Eastep</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <pubdate><?dbtimestamp format="Y/m/d"?></pubdate>

    <copyright>
      <year>2003-2005</year>

      <holder>Thomas M. Eastep</holder>
    </copyright>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
      document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version
      1.2 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with
      no Invariant Sections, with no Front-Cover, and with no Back-Cover
      Texts. A copy of the license is included in the section entitled
      <quote><ulink url="GnuCopyright.htm">GNU Free Documentation
      License</ulink></quote>.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </articleinfo>

  <caution>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">This article applies to Shorewall 3.0 and
    later. If you are running a version of Shorewall earlier than Shorewall
    3.0.0 then please see the documentation for that
    release.</emphasis></para>
  </caution>

  <para>Beginning with Shorewall version 1.4.8, Shorewall can interface to
  ftwall. <emphasis role="bold">ftwall</emphasis> is part of the <ulink
  url="http://p2pwall.sourceforge.net">p2pwall project</ulink> and is a
  user-space filter for applications based on the <quote>Fast Track</quote>
  peer to peer protocol. Applications using this protocol include Kazaa,
  KazaaLite, iMash and Grokster.</para>

  <para>To filter traffic from your <quote>loc</quote> zone with ftwall, you
  insert the following rules in the ESTABLISHED section of
  /etc/shorewall/rules file after any DROP or REJECT rules whose source is the
  <quote>loc</quote> zone.</para>

  <programlisting>        #ACTION SOURCE     DEST       PROTO
        QUEUE   loc        net        tcp
        QUEUE   loc        net        udp
        QUEUE   loc        $FW        udp</programlisting>

  <para>Now simply configure ftwall as described in the ftwall documentation
  and restart Shorewall.</para>

  <tip>
    <para>There are ftwall init scripts for use with
    <trademark>SUSE</trademark> and <trademark>Debian</trademark> Linux at
    <ulink
    url="http://shorewall.net/pub/shorewall/contrib/ftwall">http://shorewall.net/pub/shorewall/contrib/ftwall</ulink>.</para>
  </tip>

  <para>Shorewall verions 2.2.0 and later also include support for the ipp2p
  match facility which can be use to control P2P traffic. See the <ulink
  url="IPP2P.html">Shorewall IPP2P documentation</ulink> for details.</para>
</article>
