<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <!--$Id: template.xml 3517 2006-02-22 22:54:59Z judas_iscariote $-->

  <articleinfo>
    <title></title>

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Paul</firstname>

        <surname>Gear</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <pubdate>2006-03-18</pubdate>

    <copyright>
      <year>2006</year>

      <holder>Paul D. Gear</holder>
    </copyright>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
      document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version
      1.2 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with
      no Invariant Sections, with no Front-Cover, and with no Back-Cover
      Texts. A copy of the license is included in the section entitled
      <quote><ulink url="GnuCopyright.htm">GNU Free Documentation
      License</ulink></quote>.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </articleinfo>

  <section>
    <title>Shorewall Environment Survey 2006</title>

    <para>In early March 2006, i embarked on the jorney of surveying Shorewall
    users. Initially this sprang from my own curiosity: it seemed to me that
    the systems at work on which i was using Shorewall were bigger and more
    complex than a lot of the ones others were using, and i wanted to find out
    if there were people out there who used it like i did. As started thinking
    about the question's i would ask, i realised that i could ask a few more
    questions that might help us as a project to understand a bit more about
    all of our users.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Survey</title>

    <para>I used <ulink url="http://www.zoomerang.com">Zoomerang</ulink> to
    create the survey. It has a number of tools that make it really easy to
    create useful surveys. To get the most benefit out of Zoomerang, you have
    to subscribe to their professional version.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Take the survey</title>

      <para>The survey is still open as of this writing, and can be accessed
      at <ulink url="http://www.zoomerang.com/survey.zgi?p=WEB2253NNBCN44">the
      Zoomerang survey page</ulink>. Further participation is
      encouraged.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Survey results</title>

      <para>The <ulink
      url="http://www.zoomerang.com/reports/public_report.zgi?ID=L22KHC6BPGLS">public
      (anonymised) results</ulink> of the survey are also available. If you
      complete the survey, a link to the results is provided on the thank you
      page.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Results analysis</title>

    <para></para>

    <section>
      <title>Summary</title>

      <para>asdf</para>

      <section>
        <title>Organisations</title>

        <para>Small organisations dominate the spectrum of Shorewall users.
        The largest group (44%) was 1-10 users - mostly home LANs, based on
        the comments in that section. Ninety percent of Shorewall
        installations are in organisations with less than 500 users.</para>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>asdf</title>

      <para>asdf</para>

      <para></para>

      <section>
        <title>asdf</title>

        <para>asdf</para>

        <para>asdf</para>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Possible implications for free software projects</title>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Lessons learned about surveys</title>

    <para></para>
  </section>
</article>