<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<article id="three-interface">
  <!--$Id$-->

  <articleinfo>
    <title>Three-Interface Firewall</title>

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Tom</firstname>

        <surname>Eastep</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <pubdate><?dbtimestamp format="Y/m/d"?></pubdate>

    <copyright>
      <year>2002-2009</year>

      <holder>Thomas M. Eastep</holder>
    </copyright>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
      document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version
      1.2 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with
      no Invariant Sections, with no Front-Cover, and with no Back-Cover
      Texts. A copy of the license is included in the section entitled
      <quote><ulink url="GnuCopyright.htm">GNU Free Documentation
      License</ulink></quote>.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </articleinfo>

  <caution>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">This article applies to Shorewall 4.4 and
    later. If you are running a version of Shorewall earlier than Shorewall
    4.4.0 then please see the documentation for that
    release.</emphasis></para>
  </caution>

  <section id="Intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>Setting up a Linux system as a firewall for a small network with DMZ
    is a fairly straight-forward task if you understand the basics and follow
    the documentation.</para>

    <para>This guide doesn't attempt to acquaint you with all of the features
    of Shorewall. It rather focuses on what is required to configure Shorewall
    in one of its more popular configurations:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Linux system used as a firewall/router for a small local
        network.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Single public IP address.</para>

        <note>
          <para>If you have more than one public IP address, this is not the
          guide you want -- see the <ulink
          url="shorewall_setup_guide.htm">Shorewall Setup Guide</ulink>
          instead.</para>
        </note>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>DMZ connected to a separate Ethernet interface. The purpose of a
        DMZ is to isolate those servers that are exposed to the Internet from
        your local systems so that if one of those servers is compromised
        there is still a firewall between the hacked server and your local
        systems.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Connection through DSL, Cable Modem, ISDN, Frame Relay, dial-up,
        ...</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Here is a schematic of a typical installation.</para>

    <figure id="Figure1">
      <title>schematic of a typical installation</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/dmz1.png" format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <section id="Reqs">
      <title>Requirements</title>

      <para>Shorewall requires that you have the
      <command>iproute</command>/<command>iproute2</command> package installed
      (on <trademark>RedHat</trademark>, the package is called
      <command>iproute</command>). You can tell if this package is installed
      by the presence of an <command>ip</command> program on your firewall
      system. As <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem>, you can use
      the <command>which</command> command to check for this program:</para>

      <programlisting>[root@gateway root]# <command>which ip</command>
/sbin/ip
[root@gateway root]#</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section id="Before">
      <title>Before you start</title>

      <para>I recommend that you first read through the guide to familiarize
      yourself with what's involved then go back through it again making your
      configuration changes.</para>

      <caution>
        <para>If you edit your configuration files on a
        <trademark>Windows</trademark> system, you must save them as
        <trademark>Unix</trademark> files if your editor supports that option
        or you must run them through <command>dos2unix</command> before trying
        to use them. Similarly, if you copy a configuration file from your
        <trademark>Windows</trademark> hard drive to a floppy disk, you must
        run <command>dos2unix</command> against the copy before using it with
        Shorewall.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><ulink url="http://www.simtel.net/pub/pd/51438.html">Windows
            Version of dos2unix</ulink></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><ulink
            url="http://www.megaloman.com/%7Ehany/software/hd2u/">Linux
            Version of dos2unix</ulink></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </caution>
    </section>

    <section id="Conventions">
      <title>Conventions</title>

      <para>Points at which configuration changes are recommended are flagged
      with <inlinegraphic fileref="images/BD21298_.gif"
      format="GIF" />.</para>

      <para>Configuration notes that are unique to Debian and it's derivatives
      are marked with <inlinegraphic fileref="images/openlogo-nd-25.png"
      format="GIF" />.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="PPTP">
    <title>PPTP/ADSL</title>

    <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/BD21298_.gif" format="GIF" /></para>

    <para>If you have an ADSL Modem and you use PPTP to communicate with a
    server in that modem, you must make the <ulink
    url="PPTP.htm#PPTP_ADSL">changes recommended here</ulink> in addition to
    those detailed below. ADSL with PPTP is most commonly found in Europe,
    notably in Austria.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="Concepts">
    <title>Shorewall Concepts</title>

    <para>The configuration files for Shorewall are contained in the directory
    <filename>/etc/shorewall</filename> -- for simple setups, you will only
    need to deal with a few of these as described in this guide.</para>

    <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/BD21298_.gif" format="GIF" /></para>

    <para>After you have installed Shorewall, locate the three-interface
    Sample configuration:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>If you installed using an RPM, the samples will be in the
        Samples/three-interfaces/ subdirectory of the Shorewall documentation
        directory. If you don't know where the Shorewall documentation
        directory is, you can find the samples using this command:</para>

        <programlisting>~# rpm -ql shorewall | fgrep three-interfaces
/usr/share/doc/packages/shorewall/Samples/three-interfaces
/usr/share/doc/packages/shorewall/Samples/three-interfaces/interfaces
/usr/share/doc/packages/shorewall/Samples/three-interfaces/masq
/usr/share/doc/packages/shorewall/Samples/three-interfaces/policy
/usr/share/doc/packages/shorewall/Samples/three-interfaces/routestopped
/usr/share/doc/packages/shorewall/Samples/three-interfaces/rules
/usr/share/doc/packages/shorewall/Samples/three-interfaces/zones
~#</programlisting>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>If you installed using the tarball, the samples are in the
        Samples/three-interfaces directory in the tarball.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>If you installed using a Shorewall 3.x .deb, the samples are in
        /usr/share/doc/shorewall/examples/three-interfaces. You must install
        the shorewall-doc package.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><graphic align="left" fileref="images/openlogo-nd-25.png" />If
        you installed using a Shorewall 4.x .deb, the samples are in <emphasis
        role="bold"><filename
        class="directory">/usr/share/doc/shorewall/examples/three-interfaces</filename></emphasis>.
        You do not need the shorewall-doc package to have access to the
        samples.</para>

        <warning>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Note to Debian Users</emphasis></para>

          <para>If you install using the .deb, you will find that your
          <filename class="directory">/etc/shorewall</filename> directory is
          empty. This is intentional. The released configuration file
          skeletons may be found on your system in the directory <filename
          class="directory">/usr/share/doc/shorewall/default-config</filename>.
          Simply copy the files you need from that directory to <filename
          class="directory">/etc/shorewall</filename> and modify the
          copies.</para>
        </warning>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>As each file is introduced, I suggest that you look at the actual
    file on your system and that you look at the <ulink
    url="configuration_file_basics.htm#Manpages">man page</ulink> for that
    file. For example, to look at the man page for the
    <filename>/etc/shorewall/zones</filename> file, type <command>man
    shorewall-zones</command> at a shell prompt.</para>

    <para>Note: Beginning with Shorewall 4.4.20.1, there are versions of the
    sample files that are annotated with the corresponding manpage contents.
    These files have names ending in '.annotated'. You might choose to look at
    those files instead.</para>

    <para>Shorewall views the network where it is running as being composed of
    a set of zones. In the three-interface sample configuration, the following
    zone names are used:</para>

    <para><programlisting>#ZONE   TYPE   OPTIONS                 IN                      OUT
#                                      OPTIONS                 OPTIONS
fw      firewall
net     ipv4
loc     ipv4
dmz     ipv4</programlisting>Zone names are defined in
    <filename>/etc/shorewall/zones</filename>.</para>

    <para>Note that Shorewall recognizes the firewall system as its own zone.
    When the /etc/shorewall/zones file is processed, he name of the firewall
    zone is stored in the shell variable <firstterm>$FW</firstterm> which may
    be used throughout the Shorewall configuration to refer to the firewall
    zone.</para>

    <para>Rules about what traffic to allow and what traffic to deny are
    expressed in terms of zones.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>You express your default policy for connections from one zone to
        another zone in the <filename>/etc/shorewall/policy</filename>
        file.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>You define exceptions to those default policies in the
        <filename>/etc/shorewall/rules</filename> file.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>For each connection request entering the firewall, the request is
    first checked against the <filename>/etc/shorewall/rules</filename> file.
    If no rule in that file matches the connection request then the first
    policy in <filename>/etc/shorewall/policy</filename> that matches the
    request is applied. If there is a <ulink
    url="shorewall_extension_scripts.htm">common action</ulink> defined for
    the policy in <filename>/etc/shorewall/actions</filename> or
    <filename>/usr/share/shorewall/actions.std</filename> then that action is
    performed before the action is applied. The purpose of the common action
    is two-fold:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>It silently drops or rejects harmless common traffic that would
        otherwise clutter up your log — Broadcasts for example.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>If ensures that traffic critical to correct operation is allowed
        through the firewall — ICMP <emphasis>fragmentation-needed</emphasis>
        for example.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The <filename>/etc/shorewall/policy</filename> file included with
    the three-interface sample has the following policies:</para>

    <programlisting>#SOURCE    DEST        POLICY      LOG LEVEL    LIMIT:BURST
loc        net         ACCEPT
net        all         DROP        info
all        all         REJECT      info</programlisting>

    <important>
      <para>In the three-interface sample, the line below is included but
      commented out. If you want your firewall system to have full access to
      servers on the Internet, uncomment that line.</para>

      <programlisting>#SOURCE    DEST        POLICY      LOG LEVEL    LIMIT:BURST
$FW        net         ACCEPT</programlisting>
    </important>

    <para>The above policy will:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>allow all connection requests from your local network to the
        Internet</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>drop (ignore) all connection requests from the Internet to your
        firewall or local network</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>optionally accept all connection requests from the firewall to
        the Internet (if you uncomment the additional policy)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>reject all other connection requests.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>The word <firstterm>info</firstterm> in the LOG LEVEL column for the
    DROP and REJECT policies indicates that packets dropped or rejected under
    those policies should be <ulink url="shorewall_logging.html">logged at
    that level</ulink>.</para>

    <para>Some people want to consider their firewall to be part of their
    local network from a security perspective. If you want to do this, add
    these two policies:</para>

    <programlisting>#SOURCE    DEST        POLICY      LOG LEVEL    LIMIT:BURST
loc        $FW         ACCEPT
$FW        loc         ACCEPT</programlisting>

    <para>It is important to note that Shorewall policies (and rules) refer to
    <emphasis role="bold">connections</emphasis> and not packet flow. With the
    policies defined in the <filename
    class="directory">/etc/shorewall/policy</filename> file shown above,
    connections are allowed from the <emphasis>loc</emphasis> zone to the
    <emphasis>net</emphasis> zone even though connections are not allowed from
    the <emphasis>loc</emphasis> zone to the firewall itself.</para>

    <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/BD21298_.gif" format="GIF" /></para>

    <para>At this point, edit your <filename>/etc/shorewall/policy</filename>
    file and make any changes that you wish.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="Interfaces">
    <title>Network Interfaces</title>

    <figure id="Figure2">
      <title>DMZ</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/dmz1.png" format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The firewall has three network interfaces. Where Internet
    connectivity is through a cable or DSL <quote>Modem</quote>, the External
    Interface will be the Ethernet adapter that is connected to that
    <quote>Modem</quote> (e.g., <filename class="devicefile">eth0</filename>)
    unless you connect via <emphasis>Point-to-Point Protocol</emphasis> over
    Ethernet (PPPoE) or <emphasis>Point-to-Point Tunneling Protocol</emphasis>
    (PPTP) in which case the External Interface will be a
    <literal>ppp</literal> interface (e.g., <filename
    class="devicefile">ppp0</filename>). If you connect via a regular modem,
    your External Interface will also be <filename
    class="devicefile">ppp0</filename>. If you connect using ISDN, you
    external interface will be <filename
    class="devicefile">ippp0</filename>.</para>

    <caution>
      <para>Be sure you know which interface is your external interface. Many
      hours have been spent floundering by users who have configured the wrong
      interface. If you are unsure, then as root type <command>ip route
      ls</command> at the command line. The device listed in the last
      (default) route should be your external interface.</para>

      <para>Example:</para>

      <programlisting>root@lists:~# ip route ls
192.168.1.1 dev eth0  scope link 
192.168.2.2 dev tun0  proto kernel  scope link  src 192.168.2.1 
192.168.3.0/24 dev br0  proto kernel  scope link  src 192.168.3.254 
10.13.10.0/24 dev tun1  scope link 
192.168.2.0/24 via 192.168.2.2 dev tun0 
192.168.1.0/24 dev br0  proto kernel  scope link  src 192.168.1.254 
206.124.146.0/24 dev eth0  proto kernel  scope link  src 206.124.146.176 
10.10.10.0/24 dev tun1  scope link 
default via 206.124.146.254 dev <emphasis role="bold">eth0</emphasis> 
root@lists:~# </programlisting>

      <para>In that example, <filename class="devicefile">eth0</filename> is
      the external interface.</para>
    </caution>

    <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/BD21298_.gif" format="GIF" /></para>

    <para>I<emphasis role="bold">f your external interface is <filename
    class="devicefile">ppp0</filename> or <filename
    class="devicefile">ippp0</filename> then you will want to set
    <varname>CLAMPMSS=yes</varname> in
    <filename>/etc/shorewall/shorewall.conf</filename>.</emphasis></para>

    <para>Your Local Interface will be an Ethernet adapter (<filename
    class="devicefile">eth0</filename>, <filename
    class="devicefile">eth1</filename> or <filename
    class="devicefile">eth2</filename>) and will be connected to a hub or
    switch. Your local computers will be connected to the same switch (note:
    If you have only a single local system, you can connect the firewall
    directly to the computer using a cross-over cable).</para>

    <para>Your DMZ Interface will also be an Ethernet adapter (<filename
    class="devicefile">eth0</filename>, <filename
    class="devicefile">eth1</filename> or <filename
    class="devicefile">eth2</filename>) and will be connected to a hub or
    switch. Your DMZ computers will be connected to the same switch (note: If
    you have only a single DMZ system, you can connect the firewall directly
    to the computer using a cross-over cable).</para>

    <caution>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Do NOT connect multiple interfaces to the
      same hub or switch except for testing</emphasis>. You can test using
      this kind of configuration if you specify the <emphasis
      role="bold">arp_filter</emphasis> option or the <emphasis
      role="bold">arp_ignore</emphasis> option in
      <filename>/etc/shorewall/interfaces</filename> for all interfaces
      connected to the common hub/switch. <emphasis role="bold">Using such a
      setup with a production firewall is strongly recommended
      against</emphasis>.</para>
    </caution>

    <caution>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Do not configure a default route on your
      internal and DMZ interfaces.</emphasis> Your firewall should have
      exactly one default route via your ISP's Router.</para>
    </caution>

    <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/BD21298_.gif" format="GIF" /></para>

    <para>The Shorewall three-interface sample configuration assumes that the
    external interface is <filename class="devicefile">eth0</filename>, the
    local interface is <filename class="devicefile">eth1</filename> and the
    DMZ interface is <filename class="devicefile">eth2</filename>. If your
    configuration is different, you will have to modify the sample
    <filename>/etc/shorewall/interfaces</filename> file accordingly. While you
    are there, you may wish to review the list of options that are specified
    for the interfaces. Some hints:</para>

    <tip>
      <para>If your external interface is <filename
      class="devicefile">ppp0</filename> or <filename
      class="devicefile">ippp0</filename>, you can replace the
      <quote>detect</quote> in the second column with <quote>-</quote>
      (without the quotes).</para>
    </tip>

    <tip>
      <para>If your external interface is <filename
      class="devicefile">ppp0</filename> or <filename
      class="devicefile">ippp0</filename> or if you have a static IP address,
      you can remove <quote>dhcp</quote> from the option list.</para>
    </tip>
  </section>

  <section id="Addresses">
    <title>IP Addresses</title>

    <para>Before going further, we should say a few words about Internet
    Protocol (IP) addresses. Normally, your ISP will assign you a single
    Public IP address. This address may be assigned via the Dynamic Host
    Configuration Protocol (DHCP) or as part of establishing your connection
    when you dial in (standard modem) or establish your PPP connection. In
    rare cases, your ISP may assign you a static IP address; that means that
    you configure your firewall's external interface to use that address
    permanently. Regardless of how the address is assigned, it will be shared
    by all of your systems when you access the Internet. You will have to
    assign your own addresses for your internal network (the local and DMZ
    Interfaces on your firewall plus your other computers). RFC 1918 reserves
    several Private IP address ranges for this purpose:</para>

    <programlisting>10.0.0.0    - 10.255.255.255
172.16.0.0  - 172.31.255.255
192.168.0.0 - 192.168.255.255</programlisting>

    <para>You will want to assign your local addresses from one sub-network or
    subnet and your DMZ addresses from another subnet. For our purposes, we
    can consider a subnet to consists of a range of addresses <systemitem
    class="ipaddress">x.y.z.0</systemitem> - <systemitem
    class="ipaddress">x.y.z.255</systemitem>. Such a subnet will have a Subnet
    Mask of <systemitem class="netmask">255.255.255.0</systemitem>. The
    address <systemitem class="ipaddress">x.y.z.0</systemitem> is reserved as
    the Subnet Address and <systemitem class="netmask">x.y.z.255</systemitem>
    is reserved as the Subnet Broadcast Address. In Shorewall, a subnet is
    described using Classless InterDomain Routing (CIDR) notation with
    consists of the subnet address followed by <varname>/24</varname>. The
    <varname>24</varname> refers to the number of consecutive <quote>1</quote>
    bits from the left of the subnet mask.</para>

    <table id="Table1">
      <title>Example sub-network</title>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec align="left" />

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Range:</entry>

            <entry><systemitem class="ipaddress">10.10.10.0</systemitem> -
            <systemitem class="ipaddress">10.10.10.255</systemitem></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Subnet Address:</entry>

            <entry><systemitem
            class="ipaddress">10.10.10.0</systemitem></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Broadcast Address:</entry>

            <entry><systemitem
            class="ipaddress">10.10.10.255</systemitem></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>CIDR Notation:</entry>

            <entry><systemitem
            class="ipaddress">10.10.10.0/24</systemitem></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <para>It is conventional to assign the internal interface either the first
    usable address in the subnet (<systemitem
    class="ipaddress">10.10.10.1</systemitem> in the above example) or the
    last usable address (<systemitem
    class="ipaddress">10.10.10.254</systemitem>).</para>

    <para>One of the purposes of subnetting is to allow all computers in the
    subnet to understand which other computers can be communicated with
    directly. To communicate with systems outside of the subnetwork, systems
    send packets through a gateway (router).</para>

    <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/BD21298_.gif" format="GIF" /></para>

    <para>Your local computers (Local Computers 1 &amp; 2) should be
    configured with their default gateway set to the IP address of the
    firewall's internal interface and your DMZ computers (DMZ Computers 1
    &amp; 2) should be configured with their default gateway set to the IP
    address of the firewall's DMZ interface.</para>

    <para>The foregoing short discussion barely scratches the surface
    regarding subnetting and routing. If you are interested in learning more
    about IP addressing and routing, I highly recommend <quote>IP
    Fundamentals: What Everyone Needs to Know about Addressing &amp;
    Routing</quote>, Thomas A. Maufer, Prentice-Hall, 1999, ISBN
    0-13-975483-0.</para>

    <para>The remainder of this guide will assume that you have configured
    your network as shown here:</para>

    <figure id="Figure3">
      <title>DMZ</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/dmz2.png" />
        </imageobject>

        <caption><para>The default gateway for the DMZ computers would be
        <systemitem class="ipaddress">10.10.11.254</systemitem> and the
        default gateway for the Local computers would be <systemitem
        class="ipaddress">10.10.10.254</systemitem>.</para> <warning>
            <para>Your ISP might assign your external interface an RFC 1918
            address. If that address is in the <systemitem
            class="ipaddress">10.10.10.0/24</systemitem> subnet then you will
            need to select a DIFFERENT RFC 1918 subnet for your local network
            and if it is in the <systemitem
            class="ipaddress">10.10.11.0/24</systemitem> subnet then you will
            need to select a different RFC 1918 subnet for your DMZ.</para>
          </warning></caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section id="SNAT">
    <title>IP Masquerading (SNAT)</title>

    <para>The addresses reserved by RFC 1918 are sometimes referred to as
    non-routable because the Internet backbone routers don't forward packets
    which have an RFC-1918 destination address. When one of your local systems
    (let's assume local computer 1) sends a connection request to an Internet
    host, the firewall must perform Network Address Translation (NAT). The
    firewall rewrites the source address in the packet to be the address of
    the firewall's external interface; in other words, the firewall makes it
    look as if the firewall itself is initiating the connection. This is
    necessary so that the destination host will be able to route return
    packets back to the firewall (remember that packets whose destination
    address is reserved by RFC 1918 can't be routed across the Internet). When
    the firewall receives a return packet, it rewrites the destination address
    back to 10.10.10.1 and forwards the packet on to local computer 1.</para>

    <para>On Linux systems, the above process is often referred to as IP
    Masquerading and you will also see the term Source Network Address
    Translation (SNAT) used. Shorewall follows the convention used with
    Netfilter: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Masquerade</emphasis> describes the case where you
          let your firewall system automatically detect the external interface
          address.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>SNAT</emphasis> refers to the case when you
          explicitly specify the source address that you want outbound packets
          from your local network to use.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist> In Shorewall, both Masquerading and SNAT are configured
    with entries in the <filename
    class="directory">/etc/shorewall/</filename><filename>masq</filename>
    file.</para>

    <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/BD21298_.gif" format="GIF" /></para>

    <para>If your external firewall interface is <filename
    class="devicefile">eth0</filename> then you do not need to modify the file
    provided with the sample. Otherwise, edit <filename
    class="directory">/etc/shorewall/</filename><filename>masq</filename> and
    change it to match your configuration.</para>

    <para>If, in spite of all advice to the contrary, you are using this guide
    and want to use one-to-one NAT or Proxy ARP for your DMZ, you will need to
    modify the SOURCE column to list just your local interface (10.10.10.0/24
    in the above example).</para>

    <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/BD21298_.gif" format="GIF" /></para>

    <para>If your external IP is static, you can enter it in the third column
    in the <filename
    class="directory">/etc/shorewall/</filename><filename>masq</filename>
    entry if you like although your firewall will work fine if you leave that
    column empty. Entering your static IP in column 3 makes processing
    outgoing packets a little more efficient.<graphic align="left"
    fileref="images/openlogo-nd-25.png" /></para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">If you are using the Debian package, please
    check your <filename>shorewall.conf</filename> file to ensure that the
    following is set correctly; if it is not, change it appropriately:
    </emphasis><itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><varname>IP_FORWARDING=On</varname></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>
  </section>

  <section id="Logging">
    <title>Logging</title>

    <para>Shorewall does not maintain a log itself but rather relies on your
    <ulink url="shorewall_logging.htm">system's logging configuration</ulink>.
    The following <ulink url="manpages/shorewall.html">commands</ulink> rely
    on knowing where Netfilter messages are logged:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><command>shorewall show log</command> (Displays the last 20
        Netfilter log messages)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><command>shorewall logwatch</command> (Polls the log at a
        settable interval</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><command>shorewall dump</command> (Produces an extensive report
        for inclusion in Shorewall problem reports)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>It is important that these commands work properly because when you
    encounter connection problems when Shorewall is running, the first thing
    that you should do is to look at the Netfilter log; with the help of
    <ulink url="FAQ.htm#faq17">Shorewall FAQ 17</ulink>, you can usually
    resolve the problem quickly.</para>

    <para>The Netfilter log location is distribution-dependent:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Debian and its derivatives log Netfilter messages to
        <filename>/var/log/kern.log</filename>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Recent <trademark>SuSE/OpenSuSE</trademark> releases come
        preconfigured with syslog-ng and log netfilter messages to
        <filename>/var/log/firewall</filename>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>For other distributions, Netfilter messages are most commonly
        logged to <filename>/var/log/messages</filename>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/BD21298_.gif" format="GIF" /></para>

    <para>If you are running a distribution that logs netfilter messages to a
    log other than <filename>/var/log/messages</filename>, then modify the
    LOGFILE setting in <filename>/etc/shorewall/shorewall.conf</filename> to
    specify the name of your log.</para>

    <important>
      <para>The LOGFILE setting does not control where the Netfilter log is
      maintained -- it simply tells the /sbin/<filename>shorewall</filename>
      utility where to find the log.</para>
    </important>
  </section>

  <section id="Modules">
    <title>Kernel Module Loading</title>

    <para>Beginning in Shorewall 4.4.7,
    <filename>/etc/shorewall/shorewall.conf</filename> contains a
    LOAD_HELPERS_ONLY option which is set to <option>Yes</option> in the
    samples. This causes Shorewall to attempt to load the modules listed in
    <filename>/usr/share/shorewall/helpers</filename>. In addition, it sets
    <emphasis role="bold">sip_direct_media=0</emphasis> when loading the
    nf_conntrack_sip module. That setting is somewhat less secure than
    <emphasis role="bold">sip_direct_media=1</emphasis>, but it generally
    makes VOIP through the firewall work much better.</para>

    <para>The modules in <filename>/usr/share/shorewall/helpers</filename> are
    those that are not autoloaded. If your kernel does not support module
    autoloading and you want Shorewall to attempt to load all netfilter
    modules that it might require, then set LOAD_HELPERS_ONLY=No. That will
    cause Shorewall to try to load the modules listed in
    <filename>/usr/share/shorewall/modules</filename>. That file does not set
    <emphasis role="bold">sip_direct_media=0</emphasis>.</para>

    <para>If you need to modify either
    <filename>/usr/share/shorewall/helpers</filename> or
    <filename>/usr/share/shorewall/modules</filename> then copy the file to
    <filename>/etc/shorewall</filename> and modify the copy.</para>

    <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/BD21298_.gif" format="GIF" /></para>

    <para>Modify the setting of LOAD_HELPER_ONLY as necessary.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="DNAT">
    <title>Port Forwarding (DNAT)</title>

    <para>One of your goals will be to run one or more servers on your DMZ
    computers. Because these computers have RFC-1918 addresses, it is not
    possible for clients on the Internet to connect directly to them. It is
    rather necessary for those clients to address their connection requests to
    your firewall who rewrites the destination address to the address of your
    server and forwards the packet to that server. When your server responds,
    the firewall automatically performs SNAT to rewrite the source address in
    the response.</para>

    <para>The above process is called <emphasis>Port Forwarding</emphasis> or
    <emphasis>Destination Network Address Translation</emphasis> (DNAT). You
    configure port forwarding using DNAT rules in the <filename
    class="directory">/etc/shorewall/</filename><filename>rules</filename>
    file.</para>

    <para>The general form of a simple port forwarding rule in <filename
    class="directory">/etc/shorewall/</filename><filename>rules</filename> is:
    <programlisting>#ACTION   SOURCE    DEST                                          PROTO      DEST PORT(S)
DNAT      net       dmz:<emphasis>&lt;server local IP address&gt;</emphasis>[:<emphasis>&lt;server port&gt;</emphasis>] <emphasis>&lt;protocol&gt;</emphasis> <emphasis>&lt;port&gt;</emphasis></programlisting>
    If you don't specify the <emphasis><varname>&lt;server
    port&gt;</varname></emphasis>, it is assumed to be the same as
    <emphasis><varname>&lt;port&gt;</varname></emphasis>.</para>

    <important>
      <para>Be sure to add your rules after the line that reads <emphasis
      role="bold">SECTION NEW.</emphasis></para>
    </important>

    <example id="Example1">
      <title>You run a Web Server on DMZ Computer 2 and you want to forward
      incoming TCP port 80 to that system</title>

      <para><programlisting>#ACTION     SOURCE    DEST                PROTO      DEST PORT(S)
Web(DNAT)   net    dmz:10.10.11.2  
Web(ACCEPT)  loc    dmz:10.10.11.2</programlisting><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Entry 1 forwards port 80 from the Internet.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Entry 2 allows connections from the local network.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist> Several important points to keep in mind:<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>When you are connecting to your server from your local
            systems, you must use the server's internal IP address
            (<systemitem class="ipaddress">10.10.11.2</systemitem>) or you
            must use DNAT from the loc zone as well (see below).</para>

            <programlisting>#ACTION     SOURCE    DEST                PROTO      DEST          SOURCE           ORIGINAL
#                                                    PORT(S)       PORT(S)          DEST
Web(DNAT)   loc       dmz:10.10.11.2      -          -             -                <replaceable>external-ip-address</replaceable></programlisting>

            <para>where <replaceable>external-ip-address</replaceable> is the
            IP address of the firewall's external interface.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Many ISPs block incoming connection requests to port 80. If
            you have problems connecting to your web server, try the following
            rule and try connecting to port 5000 (e.g., connect to
            <literal>http://w.x.y.z:5000 where w.x.y.z</literal> is your
            external IP).<programlisting>#ACTION   SOURCE    DEST                PROTO      DEST PORT(S)    SOURCE
#                                                                  PORT(S)
DNAT      net       dmz:10.10.11.2:80   tcp        5000</programlisting></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>If you want to be able to access your server from the local
            network using your external address, then if you have a static
            external IP you can replace the loc-&gt;dmz rule above
            with:<programlisting>#ACTION   SOURCE    DEST            PROTO  DEST PORT(S)  SOURCE   ORIGINAL
#                                                        PORT(S)  DEST
DNAT      loc       dmz:10.10.11.2  tcp    80            -        <emphasis>&lt;external IP&gt;</emphasis></programlisting>If
            you have a dynamic IP then you must ensure that your external
            interface is up before starting Shorewall and you must take steps
            as follows (assume that your external interface is <filename
            class="devicefile">eth0</filename>):<orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Include the following in /etc/shorewall/params:</para>

                  <para><command>ETH0_IP=$(find_interface_address
                  eth0)</command></para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Make your <literal>loc-&gt;dmz</literal> rule:
                  <programlisting>#ACTION   SOURCE    DEST             PROTO   DEST PORT(S)  SOURCE   ORIGINAL
#                                                          PORT(S)  DEST
DNAT      loc       dmz:10.10.11.2   tcp     80            -        $ETH0_IP</programlisting></para>
                </listitem>
              </orderedlist></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>If you want to access your server from the DMZ using your
            external IP address, see <ulink url="FAQ.htm#faq2a">FAQ
            2a</ulink>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </example>

    <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/BD21298_.gif" format="GIF" /></para>

    <para>At this point, add the DNAT and ACCEPT rules for your
    servers.</para>

    <important>
      <para>When testing DNAT rules like those shown above, you must test from
      a client OUTSIDE YOUR FIREWALL (in the 'net' zone). You cannot test
      these rules from inside the firewall!</para>

      <para>For DNAT troubleshooting tips, <ulink url="FAQ.htm#faq1a">see FAQs
      1a and 1b</ulink>.</para>
    </important>
  </section>

  <section id="DNS">
    <title>Domain Name Server (DNS)</title>

    <para>Normally, when you connect to your ISP, as part of getting an IP
    address your firewall's <emphasis>Domain Name Service</emphasis> (DNS)
    resolver will be automatically configured (e.g., the
    <filename>/etc/resolv.conf</filename> file will be written).
    Alternatively, your ISP may have given you the IP address of a pair of DNS
    name servers for you to manually configure as your primary and secondary
    name servers. It is your responsibility to configure the resolver in your
    internal systems. You can take one of two approaches: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>You can configure your internal systems to use your ISP's name
          servers. If your ISP gave you the addresses of their servers or if
          those addresses are available on their web site, you can configure
          your internal systems to use those addresses. If that information
          isn't available, look in <filename>/etc/resolv.conf</filename> on
          your firewall system -- the name servers are given in
          <quote>nameserver</quote> records in that file.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/BD21298_.gif"
          format="GIF" /></para>

          <para>You can configure a <emphasis>Caching Name Server</emphasis>
          on your firewall or in your DMZ. <trademark>Red Hat</trademark> has
          an RPM for a caching name server (which also requires the
          '<command>bind</command>' RPM) and for Bering users, there is
          <filename>dnscache.lrp</filename>. If you take this approach, you
          configure your internal systems to use the caching name server as
          their primary (and only) name server. You use the internal IP
          address of the firewall (<systemitem
          class="ipaddress">10.10.10.254</systemitem> in the example above)
          for the name server address if you choose to run the name server on
          your firewall. To allow your local systems to talk to your caching
          name server, you must open port 53 (both UDP and TCP) from the local
          network to the server; you do that by adding the rules in
          <filename>/etc/shorewall/rules</filename>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist> If you run the name server on the firewall:
    <programlisting>#ACTION     SOURCE    DEST                PROTO      DEST PORT(S)                      
DNS(ACCEPT) loc       $FW
DNS(ACCEPT) dmz       $FW            </programlisting> Run name server on DMZ
    computer 1: <programlisting>#ACTION     SOURCE    DEST                PROTO      DEST PORT(S)                      
DNS(ACCEPT) loc       dmz:10.10.11.1
DNS(ACCEPT) $FW       dmz:10.10.11.1             </programlisting></para>

    <para>In the rules shown above, <quote>DNS</quote>(ACCEPT)is an example of
    a <emphasis>defined macro</emphasis>. Shorewall includes a number of
    defined macros and <ulink url="Macros.html">you can add your own</ulink>.
    To see the list of macros included with your version of Shorewall, run the
    command <command>ls
    <filename>/usr/share/shorewall/macro.*</filename></command>.</para>

    <para>You don't have to use defined macros when coding a rule in
    <filename>/etc/shorewall/rules</filename>. The first example above (name
    server on the firewall) could also have been coded as follows:</para>

    <programlisting>#ACTION   SOURCE    DEST                PROTO      DEST PORT(S)                      
ACCEPT    loc       $FW                 tcp        53
ACCEPT    loc       $FW                 udp        53
ACCEPT    dmz       $FW                 tcp        53
ACCEPT    dmz       $FW                 udp        53              </programlisting>

    <para>In cases where Shorewall doesn't include a defined macro to meet
    your needs, you can either define the macro yourself or you can simply
    code the appropriate rules directly. <ulink url="ports.html">This
    page</ulink> can be of help if you don't know the protocol and port
    involved.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="Open">
    <title>Other Connections</title>

    <para>The three-interface sample includes the following rule:
    <programlisting>#ACTION     SOURCE    DEST                PROTO      DEST PORT(S)                      
DNS(ACCEPT) $FW       net       </programlisting>That rule allow DNS access
    from your firewall and may be removed if you commented out the line in
    <filename>/etc/shorewall/policy</filename> allowing all connections from
    the firewall to the Internet.</para>

    <para>The sample also includes: <programlisting>#ACTION     SOURCE    DEST                PROTO      DEST PORT(S)                      
SSH(ACCEPT) loc       $FW
SSH(ACCEPT) loc       dmz        </programlisting>Those rules allow you to run
    an SSH server on your firewall and in each of your DMZ systems and to
    connect to those servers from your local systems.</para>

    <para>If you wish to enable other connections between your systems, the
    general format for using a defined macro is: <programlisting>#ACTION         SOURCE        DEST                PROTO      DEST PORT(S)                      
&lt;<emphasis>macro</emphasis>&gt;(ACCEPT) <emphasis>&lt;source zone&gt; &lt;destination zone&gt;</emphasis></programlisting></para>

    <para>The general format when not using a defined macro
    is:<programlisting>#ACTION   SOURCE        DEST                PROTO      DEST PORT(S)                      
ACCEPT    <emphasis>&lt;source zone&gt; &lt;destination zone&gt;  &lt;protocol&gt; &lt;port&gt; </emphasis></programlisting></para>

    <example id="Example2">
      <title>You want to run a publicly-available DNS server on your firewall
      system</title>

      <para>Using defined macros:</para>

      <programlisting>#ACTION     SOURCE    DEST                PROTO      DEST PORT(S)
DNS(ACCEPT) net       $FW</programlisting>

      <para>Not using defined macros:</para>

      <programlisting>#ACTION   SOURCE    DEST                PROTO      DEST PORT(S)                      
ACCEPT    net       $FW                 tcp        53
ACCEPT    net       $FW                 udp        53        </programlisting>

      <para>Those rules would of course be in addition to the rules listed
      above under "If you run the name server on your firewall".</para>
    </example>

    <para>If you don't know what port and protocol a particular application
    uses, <ulink url="ports.htm">look here</ulink>.</para>

    <important>
      <para>I don't recommend enabling telnet to/from the Internet because it
      uses clear text (even for login!). If you want shell access to your
      firewall from the Internet, use SSH: <programlisting>#ACTION     SOURCE    DEST                PROTO      DEST PORT(S)                      
SSH(ACCEPT) net       $FW</programlisting></para>
    </important>

    <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/leaflogo.gif" format="GIF" /> Bering
    users will want to add the following two rules to be compatible with
    Jacques's Shorewall configuration: <programlisting>#ACTION   SOURCE    DEST                PROTO      DEST PORT(S)                      
ACCEPT    loc       $FW                 udp        53
ACCEPT    net       $FW                 tcp        80       </programlisting><itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Entry 1 allows the DNS Cache to be used.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Entry 2 allows the <quote>weblet</quote> to work.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist><inlinegraphic fileref="images/BD21298_.gif"
    format="GIF" /></para>

    <para>Now modify <filename>/etc/shorewall/rules</filename> to add or
    remove other connections as required.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="Other">
    <title>Some Things to Keep in Mind</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">You cannot test your firewall from the
        inside</emphasis>. Just because you send requests to your firewall
        external IP address does not mean that the request will be associated
        with the external interface or the <quote>net</quote> zone. Any
        traffic that you generate from the local network will be associated
        with your local interface and will be treated as loc-&gt;fw
        traffic.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">IP addresses are properties of systems,
        not of interfaces</emphasis>. It is a mistake to believe that your
        firewall is able to forward packets just because you can ping the IP
        address of all of the firewall's interfaces from the local network.
        The only conclusion you can draw from such pinging success is that the
        link between the local system and the firewall works and that you
        probably have the local system's default gateway set correctly.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">All IP addresses configured on firewall
        interfaces are in the $FW (fw) zone</emphasis>. If 192.168.1.254 is
        the IP address of your internal interface then you can write
        <quote><emphasis role="bold">$FW:192.168.1.254</emphasis></quote> in a
        rule but you may not write <quote><emphasis
        role="bold">loc:192.168.1.254</emphasis></quote>. Similarly, it is
        nonsensical to add 192.168.1.254 to the <emphasis
        role="bold">loc</emphasis> zone using an entry in
        <filename>/etc/shorewall/hosts</filename>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Reply packets do NOT automatically follow
        the reverse path of the one taken by the original request</emphasis>.
        All packets are routed according to the routing table of the host at
        each step of the way. This issue commonly comes up when people install
        a Shorewall firewall parallel to an existing gateway and try to use
        DNAT through Shorewall without changing the default gateway of the
        system receiving the forwarded requests. Requests come in through the
        Shorewall firewall where the destination IP address gets rewritten but
        replies go out unmodified through the old gateway.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Shorewall itself has no notion of inside
        or outside</emphasis>. These concepts are embodied in how Shorewall is
        configured.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Disabling your existing Firewall</title>

    <para>Before starting Shorewall for the first time, it's a good idea to
    stop your existing firewall. On Redhat/CentOS/Fedora:</para>

    <programlisting><command>service iptables stop</command></programlisting>

    <para>If you are running SuSE, use Yast or Yast2 to stop
    SuSEFirewall.</para>

    <para>Once you have Shorewall running to your satisfaction, you should
    totally disable your existing firewall. On /Redhat/CentOS/Fedora:</para>

    <programlisting><command>chkconfig --del iptables</command></programlisting>
  </section>

  <section id="Starting">
    <title>Starting and Stopping Your Firewall</title>

    <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/BD21298_.gif" format="GIF" /></para>

    <para>The <ulink url="Install.htm">installation procedure</ulink>
    configures your system to start Shorewall at system boot but startup is
    disabled so that your system won't try to start Shorewall before
    configuration is complete. Once you have completed configuration of your
    firewall, you can enable Shorewall startup by editing
    <filename>/etc/shorewall/shorewall.conf</filename> and setting
    STARTUP_ENABLED=Yes.<graphic align="left"
    fileref="images/openlogo-nd-25.png" /><important>
        <para>Users of the <filename>.deb</filename> package must edit
        <filename>/etc/default/shorewall</filename> and set
        <varname>startup=1</varname>.</para>
      </important></para>

    <para>While you are editing <filename>shorewall.conf</filename>, it is a
    good idea to check the value of the SUBSYSLOCK option. You can find a
    description of this option by typing 'man shorewall.conf' at a shell
    prompt and searching for SUBSYSLOCK</para>

    <para>The firewall is started using the <command>shorewall start</command>
    command and stopped using <command>shorewall stop</command>. When the
    firewall is stopped, routing is enabled on those hosts that have an entry
    in <ulink
    url="manpages/shorewall-routestopped.html"><filename>/etc/shorewall/routestopped</filename></ulink>.
    A running firewall may be restarted using the <command>shorewall
    restart</command> command. If you want to totally remove any trace of
    Shorewall from your Netfilter configuration, use <command>shorewall
    clear</command>.</para>

    <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/BD21298_.gif" format="GIF" /></para>

    <para>The three-interface sample assumes that you want to enable routing
    to/from <filename class="devicefile">eth1</filename> (your local network)
    and <filename class="devicefile">eth2</filename> (DMZ) when Shorewall is
    stopped. If these two interfaces don't connect to your local network and
    DMZ or if you want to enable a different set of hosts, modify
    <filename>/etc/shorewall/routestopped</filename> accordingly. <warning>
        <para>If you are connected to your firewall from the Internet, do not
        issue a <command>shorewall stop</command> command unless you have
        added an entry for the IP address that you are connected from to
        <ulink
        url="manpages/shorewall-routestopped.html"><filename>/etc/shorewall/routestopped</filename></ulink>.
        Also, I don't recommend using <command>shorewall restart</command>; it
        is better to create an <ulink
        url="configuration_file_basics.htm#Levels">alternate
        configuration</ulink> and test it using the <ulink
        url="starting_and_stopping_shorewall.htm"><command>shorewall
        try</command> command</ulink>.</para>
      </warning></para>

    <para>The firewall will start after your network interfaces have been
    brought up. This leaves a small window between the time that the network
    interface are working and when the firewall is controlling connections
    through those interfaces. If this is a concern, you can close that window
    by installing the <ulink url="Shorewall-init.html">Shorewall Init
    Package</ulink>.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="Trouble">
    <title>If it Doesn't Work</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Re-check each of the items flagged with a red arrow
        above.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Check your <ulink
        url="shorewall_logging.html">log</ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Check the <ulink url="troubleshoot.htm">Troubleshooting
        Guide</ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Check the <ulink url="FAQ.htm">FAQ</ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="Reading">
    <title>Additional Recommended Reading</title>

    <para>I highly recommend that you review the <ulink
    url="configuration_file_basics.htm">Common Configuration File
    Features</ulink> page -- it contains helpful tips about Shorewall features
    than make administering your firewall easier. Also, <ulink
    url="starting_and_stopping_shorewall.htm">Operating Shorewall and
    Shorewall Lite</ulink> contains a lot of useful operational hints.</para>
  </section>
</article>
