<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <!--$Id$-->

  <articleinfo>
    <title>Shorewall and UPnP</title>

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Tom</firstname>

        <surname>Eastep</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <pubdate><?dbtimestamp format="Y/m/d"?></pubdate>

    <copyright>
      <year>2005</year>

      <year>2010</year>

      <year>2013</year>

      <holder>Thomas M. Eastep</holder>
    </copyright>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
      document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version
      1.2 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with
      no Invariant Sections, with no Front-Cover, and with no Back-Cover
      Texts. A copy of the license is included in the section entitled
      <quote><ulink url="GnuCopyright.htm">GNU Free Documentation
      License</ulink></quote>.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </articleinfo>

  <section id="UPnP">
    <title>UPnP</title>

    <para>Shorewall includes support for UPnP (Universal Plug and Play) using
    linux-igd (<ulink
    url="http://linux-igd.sourceforge.net">http://linux-igd.sourceforge.net</ulink>).
    UPnP is required by a number of popular applications including MSN
    IM.</para>

    <warning>
      <para>From a security architecture viewpoint, UPnP is a disaster. It
      assumes that:</para>

      <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
        <listitem>
          <para>All local systems and their users are completely
          trustworthy.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>No local system is infected with any worm or trojan.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>If either of these assumptions are not true then UPnP can be used
      to totally defeat your firewall and to allow incoming connections to
      arbitrary local systems on any port whatsoever. In short: USE UPnP
      <emphasis role="bold">AT YOUR OWN RISK.</emphasis></para>
    </warning>

    <important>
      <para>Shorewall and linux-igd implement a UPnP <firstterm>Internet
      Gateway Device</firstterm>. It will not allow clients on one LAN subnet
      to access a UPnP Media Server on another subnet.</para>
    </important>
  </section>

  <section id="linux-igd">
    <title>linux-igd Configuration</title>

    <para>In /etc/upnpd.conf, you will want:</para>

    <programlisting>create_forward_rules = yes
prerouting_chain_name = UPnP
forward_chain_name = forwardUPnP</programlisting>
  </section>

  <section id="Shorewall">
    <title>Shorewall Configuration</title>

    <para>In <filename>/etc/shorewall/interfaces</filename>, you need the
    'upnp' option on your external interface.</para>

    <para>Example:</para>

    <programlisting>#ZONE   INTERFACE       BROADCAST       OPTIONS
net     eth1            detect          dhcp,routefilter,tcpflags,<emphasis
        role="bold">upnp</emphasis></programlisting>

    <para>If your loc-&gt;fw policy is not ACCEPT then you need this
    rule:</para>

    <programlisting>#ACTION            SOURCE  DEST
allowinUPnP        loc     $FW</programlisting>

    <para>You MUST have this rule:</para>

    <programlisting>#ACTION            SOURCE  DEST
forwardUPnP        net     loc</programlisting>

    <para>You must also ensure that you have a route to 224.0.0.0/4 on your
    internal (local) interface as described in the linux-igd
    documentation.</para>

    <note>
      <para>The init script included with the Debian linux-idg package adds
      this route during <command>start</command> and deletes it during
      <command>stop</command>.</para>
    </note>

    <caution>
      <para>Shorewall versions prior to 4.4.10 do not retain the dynamic rules
      added by linux-idg over a <command>shorewall restart</command>.</para>
    </caution>

    <para>If your firewall-&gt;loc policy is not ACCEPT, then you also need to
    allow UDP traffic from the fireawll to the local zone.</para>

    <programlisting>ACCEPT      $FW          loc        udp            -         &lt;<replaceable>dynamic port range</replaceable>&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>The dynamic port range is obtained by <emphasis role="bold">cat
    /proc/sys/net/ip_local_port_range</emphasis>.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Shorewall on a UPnP Client</title>

    <para>It is sometimes desirable to run UPnP-enabled client programs like
    <ulink url="http://www.transmissionbt.com/">Transmission</ulink>
    (BitTorrent client) on a Shorewall-protected system. Shorewall provides
    support for UPnP client access in the form of the <emphasis
    role="bold">upnpclient</emphasis> option in <ulink
    url="manpages/shorewall-interfaces.html">shorewall-interfaces</ulink>
    (5).</para>

    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">upnpclient</emphasis> option causes
    Shorewall to detect the default gateway through the interface and to
    accept UDP packets from that gateway. Note that, like all aspects of UPnP,
    this is a security hole so use this option at your own risk.</para>

    <para>Note that when multiple clients behind the firewall use UPnP, they
    must configure their applications to use unique ports.</para>
  </section>
</article>
